today I'd like to talk about GO which
is interesting especially interesting
for us in this course because course GO
is the language at the labs you're all
going to do the labs in and so I want to
focus today particularly on some of the
machinery that sort of most useful in
the labs and in most particular to
distributed programming um first of all
you know it's worth asking why we use go
in this class in fact we could have used
any one of a number of other system
style languages plenty languages like
Java or C sharp or even Python that
provide the kind of facilities we need
and indeed we used to use C++ in this
class and it worked out fine it'll go
indeed like many other languages
provides a bunch of features which are
particularly convenient
that's good support for threads and
locking and synchronization between
threads which we use a lot it is a
convenient remote procedure call package
which doesn't sound like much but it
actually turns out to be a significant
constraint from in languages like C++
for example it's actually a bit hard to
find a convenient easy to use remote
procedure call package and of course we
use it all the time in this course or
programs and different machines to talk
to each other unlike C++ go is type safe
and memory safe that is it's pretty hard
to write a program that due to a bug
scribbles over some random piece of
memory and then causes the program to do
mysterious things and that just
eliminates a big class of bugs similarly
it's garbage collected which means you
never in danger of priam the same memory
twice or free memory that's still in use
or something the garbage vector just
frees things when they stop being used
and one thing it's maybe not obvious
until you played around with just this
kind of programming before but the
combination of threads and garbage
collection is particularly important one
of the things that goes wrong in a non
garbage collected language like C++ if
you use threads is that it's always a
bit of a puzzle and requires a bunch of
bookkeeping to figure out when the last
thread
that's using a shared object has
finished using that object because only
then can you free the object as you end
up writing quite a bit of coat it's like
manually the programmer it's about a
bunch of code to manually you know do
reference counting or something in order
to figure out you know when the last
thread stopped using an object and
that's just a pain and that problem
completely goes away if you use garbage
collection like we haven't go
and finally the language is simple much
simpler than C++ one of the problems
with using C++ is that often if you made
an error you know maybe even just a typo
the the error message you get back from
the compiler is so complicated that in
C++ it's usually not worth trying to
figure out what the error message meant
and I find it's always just much quicker
to go look at the line number and try to
guess what the error must have been
because the language is far too
complicated
whereas go is you know probably doesn't
have a lot of people's favorite features
but it's relatively straightforward
language okay so at this point you're
both on the tutorial if you're looking
for sort of you know what to look at
next to learn about the language a good
place to look is the document titled
effective go which you know you can find
by searching the web all right the first
thing I want to talk about is threads
the reason why we care a lot about
threads in this course is that threads
are the sort of main tool we're going to
be using to manage concurrency in
programs and concurrency is a particular
interest in distributed programming
because it's often the case that one
program actually needs to talk to a
bunch of other computers you know client
may talk to many servers or a server may
be serving requests at the same time on
behalf of many different clients and so
we need a way to say oh you know I'm my
program really has seven different
things going on because it's talking to
seven different clients and I want a
simple way to allow it to do these seven
different things you know without too
much complex programming I mean sort of
thrust threads are the answer so these
are the things that the go documentation
calls go routines which I call threads
they're go routines are really this same
as what everybody else calls
Red's so the way to think of threads is
that you have a program of one program
and one address space I'm gonna draw a
box to sort of denote an address space
and within that address space in a
serial program without threads you just
have one thread of execution executing
code in that address space one program
counter one set of registers one stack
that are sort of describing the current
state of the execution in a threaded